Finding aid for Bentley Historical Library records, 1919 - 2014
Bentley Historical Library
- Audio-Visual Material
  - Works of Art: Inventory and Object Files
    - Decorative Arts
      - Rug (Caucasus), 19th Century (Box 52)
      - Tapestry (French or Flemish), circa 1500 (Box 52)
      - Tea Service (Silver), 1976 (Box 52)
      - Vase with Masonic symbols, 20th Century (Box 52)
      - Vase, Royal Copenhagen, 1976 (Box 52)
    - Artist Name (Known)
      - Bates, Marston, drawings (Box 52)
      - Bainbridge, P.J., 1817-1881 (Box 52)
      - Balch (after Goodwin), Vistus James G. Birney (Box 52)
      - Bradish, Alvah, Portraits of Douglas Houghton (Box 52)
      - Bradish, Alvah, Portraits of Abraham Lincoln (Box 52)
      - Brown, E., Jr. (Box 52)
      - Burger, R. (Lithograph) (Box 52)
      - Clark School Diploma (Box 52)
      - Cropsey, J.F.
        - General (Box 52)
        - Leggett after View of Ann Arbor (Box 52)
        - Object File, Detroit Observatory (Box 52)
        - Object File, University of Michigan campus (Box 52)
        - Sketchbook (Box 52)
        - View of University of Michigan campus (pencil) (Box 52)
      - Cushing, George (Glass Discs) (Box 52)
      - de Lery, J.G.C. (after de Lery) Map of Detroit (Box 52)
      - Dolan, Cartoons (P.A. Hart Collection) (Box 52)
      - Edwards, W.J. (Lewis Cass Portrait) (Box 52)
      - Gentilly, Head of F.M. Casto (bronze) (Box 52)
      - Goodrich, Osman Dewey, 1808-1887 (Box 52)
      - Graf, Fred, cartoon, (P.A. Hart collection) (Box 52)
      - Hansen, Ralph, portrait of R.W. Fleming (Box 52)
      - Haynie, Hugh, cartoon (P.A. Hart collection) (Box 52)
      - Hickham after de Lery map (carte de la riviere du Detroit) (Box 52)
      - Hinschelwood, Robert, City of Detroit A.C. Warren, 1872 (Box 52)
      - Hunt, Richard, Historical Circle Peregrine Section (Box 52)
      - Ives, Lewis Tomas, Portrait of Aaron Burr Maynard (Box 52)
      - Keesee, Vincent, Oil painting of Stellanova Osborn at Duck Island (Box 52)
      - Kent, Rockwell, Vulcan (Box 52)
      - Kidjel, M., Portrait of Frank Murphy (Box 52)
      - Krumbien, JR (Box 52)
      - Lorch, Emil, 1870-1963 (Box 52)
      - Maniscalco, Portrait of Arthur H. Vandenberg (Box 52)
      - Maniscalco, Portrait of Louis G. VanderVelde (Box 52)
      - Mason, Stevens T. Portrait (posthumous copy) (Box 52)
      - Mead, Adeline B., View of the Michigan University from the NE (Box 52)
      - Melchers, Gary, Portrait of Chase S. Osborn (Box 52)
      - Moore, S., Portrait of Thomas McIntyre Cooley (Box 52)
      - Norman, DoLoria Work from Kahlil Gibran's "The Prophet" (Box 52)
      - Ohrn, David W., President's House terrace (Box 52)
      - Parker, Jordan A., cartoon (P.A. Hart Collection) (Box 52)
      - Parsons, Charles, Detroit, Michigan (panoramic view) (Box 52)
      - Philippine, Portrait of Jose Rizal, 1861-1896 (Box 52)
      - Poinier, Art, cartoon (P.A. Hart collection) (Box 52)
      - Queen, James F., Washington lithograph (Box 52)
      - Rasmussen, Geraldine (Box 52)
      - Roedel, H., Ora Labora, Michigan (Box 52)
      - Rogers, Katie J., Portrait of Mina Mae Doty (Box 52)
      - Rogers, Winifred, Portrait of Stella Brunt Osborn (Box 52)
      - Rosenthal, L.N., Camp Union (Lithograph), 1861 (Box 52)
      - Sartain, Samuel, Crapo Engraving (Box 52)
      - Schlatter, William and Michael (Box 52)
      - Shaw, Horatio W.
        - Campus and Town (Etchings) (Box 52)
        - General (Box 52)
        - Robert Frost (Drawing) (Box 52)
        - Shaw Cabin, Michigan Territory (Box 52)
        - Shaw Homestead, Dover, Michigan (Box 52)
        - University of Michigan-Notables (Etchings) (Box 52)
      - Smith, Alvin, Portrait of Stevens T. Mason (Box 52)
      - Sullivan, Louis H.
        - Conservation Records (Box 52)
        - Drawings (Box 52)
        - Exhibit Catalog Louis Sullivan: The Function of Ornament, Chicago Historical Society (items lent for exhibit), 1986-1987 (Box 52)
        - General (Box 52)
      - Tarbell (Box 52)
      - Tenny, Mark Wayland (Box 52)
      - Thom, Robert Freemasonry's Role in the Founding of the University of Michigan, 1967 (Box 52)
      - Tiede, M., Astronomical Clock, circa 1853-1854 (Box 52)
      - Valzman, School of Music Building (Box 52)
      - Von Kann, Kitty, Portrait of Wilber M. Brucker (oil) (Box 52)
      - Walsh, P. Detroit from the Straits, (reproduction) (Box 52)
      - Walk-in-the Water (lithograph) (Box 52)
      - Williams, G. Mennen (Drawings from the Collection of G. Mennen Williams) (Box 52)
      - Woodware, Bechthold (Box 52)
      - Wenner, Violet B., Portrait of Floyd Starr (Box 52)
      - Whipple, S.A. Champion (chromolithograph) (Box 52)
      - Yost, Eunice F., Portrait of Frank Murphy (Box 52)
      - Young, Portrait of Gerald R. Ford (Box 52)
  - Photographs, 1967-1998
    Included in the Photographs series are images documenting the construction of the BHL and various ceremonies and dedications commemorating the building in the early 1970s, including several interior and exterior views by Balthazar Korab. There are also a number of files of photographs of major exhibits mounted by BHL staff, copy prints and negatives of images used in BHL publications, and informal snapshots of events, visitors and staff. The Audiotapes and Videotapes, Films, DVD's, and Digital Media series document dedications, important meetings and events, and the laying of the cornerstone for the Bentley Library. There are two accessions of Photographs (1967-1998) and (1995-2009) and two accessions of Audiotapes and Videotapes (1971-1991) and 1987-1999).
    - Bentley Library (Box 53)
      - Architectural Drawings and Site Photographs (includes North Campus views) (Box 53)
      - Construction (Box 53)
      - Courtyard (Peter Yates images), 1998 (Box 53)
      - Exteriors (Box 53)
        (includes Balthazar Korab images)
      - Interiors (Box 53)
      - Transparencies, 1987-1988 (Box 53)
    - William L. Clements Library (Box 53)
    - Horace H. Rackham Building (Box 53)
    - Willow Run Storage (Box 53)
    - Ceremonies, Dedications, etc.
      - Opening of Bids, 1972 (Box 53)
      - Masonic Check Presentation, March 16, 1972 (Box 53)
      - Friends Meeting, May 4, 1972 (Box 53)
      - Groundbreaking Ceremony, August 2, 1972 (Box 53)
      - President's Club Meeting, September 29, 1972 (Box 53)
      - Cornerstone Laying, November 17, 1972 (Box 53)
      - Dedication Luncheon and Reception, May 2, 1974 (Box 53)
      - Reading Room Dedication, May 3, 1974 (Box 53)
      - Development Council Meeting, May 23, 1974 (Box 53)
      - Dedications: Delta Sigma Delta Room October 1974 and Vander Velde Portrait, April 1975, 1974-1975 (Box 53)
      - Vander Velde Memorial Services, November 6, 1975 (Box 53)
      - Starr Room Dedication, September 17, 1977 (Box 53)
      - Stella Osborn Honorary Degree Reception, August 18, 1978 (Box 53)
      - Ford Library Groundbreaking Tea 1979 GRF Visits, 1974, 1977, 1974-1979 (Box 53)
      - Friends Tea, September 20, 1984 (Box 53)
      - Pugh, Mary Jo, Farewell Party (includes photographs), December 1984 (Box 53)
      - 50th Anniversary of the MHC, 1985 (Box 53)
      - Roscoe Bonisteel Portrait Unveiling, January 9, 1987 (Box 53)
      - Robert M. Warner Portrait Unveiling, 1989 (Box 53)
      - Collections arriving at the Library (Copeland, Ford, etc.) (Box 53)
    - Exhibit Photographs
      - Sesquicentennial Exhibit (Rackham), 1967 (Box 53)
      - Gerald R. Ford Exhibit, 1979 (Box 53)
      - University President's Exhibit, 1980 (Box 53)
      - Black Detroit and the Great Migration, 1991 (Box 53)
      - Football, 1994 (Box 53)
    - General Prints and Negatives, 1988-1999; 5 folders (Box 53)
      (includes Friends Meetings, Foreign Exchanges, Miscellaneous events, Snapshots, Visitors)
    - Publication Copy Prints, Negatives, etc
      - Ann Arbor. Pictorial History of Ann Arbor, 1974; 7 envelopes (Box 53)
      - Balita Mula Maynila, 1971 (Box 53)
      - Book of Days, Images, 1987; 35 folders (Box 53)
      - Book of Days, Transparencies, 1987; 39 envelopes (Box 53)
      - The Finns in the United States, 1976 (Box 53)
      - Immigration Sources, 1979 (Box 53)
      - Michigan Social History, 1987 (Box 53)
      - Microfilm Edition of Temperance and Prohibition Papers, Guide, 1977 (Box 53)
      - More Than a Handsome Box, 1995 (Box 53)
      - President's House, 1996 (Box 53)
      - What Is It (brochure) (Box 53)
      - The Early Years of the University of Michigan Medical School: The Upjohn Family Experience, 1982 (Box 53)
      - Various publications, 1990-1994 (Box 53)
    - Staff Photographs and Snapshots, including early pre-Bentley photographs, post-1974 staff photographs, and 1998 trip to Nanjing, China (Box 53)
    - Bentley Library
      - Construction (Box 71)
      - Exteriors, 1999 (Box 71)
    - International
      - Bentley delegation to Russia, 1994 (Box 71)
      - Chinese exchanges, circa 2009 (Box 71)
    - General
      - Kellogg Foundation, 1985 (Box 71)
      - Observatory Clock, undated (Box 71)
      - Research Fellowship Program for the Study of Modern Archives, 1983-1989; 7 folders (Box 71)
    - Publication Copy Prints
      - Ann Arbor's First Lady: Events in the life of Ann I. Allen, 1998 (Box 71)
      - Membership Brochure Photographs, 2000 (Box 71)
    - Staff photographs
      - 1998, undated (Box 71)
      - 2000 (Box 71)
      - 2013, .ZIP file
        (Includes images of facilities and collections)
  - Audiotapes and Videotapes, 1971-1991
    The Audiotapes and Videotapes, and Films series document dedications, important meetings and events, and the laying of the cornerstone for the Bentley Library.
    - Roger Heyns, Friends Meeting, November 17, 1971; 1 audiocassettes (Box 54)
    - Bentley Historical Library Dedication/groundbreaking ceremony, 1973; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel, 7 in., 3 3/4 ips) (Box 54)
    - G. M. Williams Room Dedication, 1975; 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel, 7 in., 3 3/4 ips) (Box 54)
    - Lewis G. Vander Velde Memorial Service, November 6, 1975; 1 audiocassettes (Box 54)
    - Chase S. Osborn Room Dedication, October 3, 1976; 1 audiocassettes (Box 54)
    - Robben Fleming and Robert Warner, WUOM re: Ford Library, 1976 December 14; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 5 inch, 7 1/2 ips (Box 54)
      - [Part 1], [87245-SR-1-1]; (Robben Fleming and Robert Warner regarding the announcement of the Ford Library coming to the University of Michigan.)
        [Digitized audio files are only available in the Bentley Historical Library reading room on designated Bentley Library computers.]
    - Floyd Starr Room Dedication, September 18, 1977, 1 audiocassettes, 1 audiotape (reel-to-reel, 7 in., 3 3/4 ips) (Box 54)
    - Prentiss M. Brown Room Dedication, October 16, 1977; 1 reel: 7 in., 3 3/4ips (Box 54)
    - Fritz Crisler, Friends of the Michigan Historical Collections, 1979 November 13; Audio Reel-to-Reel, 7 inch, 7 1/2 ips (Box 54)
      - [Part 1], [87245-SR-2-1]; (To Friends of the Michigan Historical Collections at Bentley Library, November 13, 1979. Introduction by Harlan Hatcher, Moderator Robert M. Warner)
    - History of Michigan Seminar and Tea with the Presidents' Wives at the Bentley Historical Library, 2 audiocassettes (Box 54)
      (A tea and conversation with the wives of two former University of Michigan Presidents and the current President (at the time of recording), including Anne Hatcher, Sally Fleming, and Vivian Shapiro, as part of the Seminars on Michigan History series hosted by the Bentley Historical Library. They discuss their lives and roles leading up to and during their husbands' presidencies.)
      - Tape 1
        - [Side 1], [87245-SR-11-1]
        - [Side 2], [87245-SR-11-2]
      - Tape 2
        - [Side 1; no Side 2], [87245-SR-12-1]
    - Kathy Koehler, WJR re: Student Life Exhibit "Talegate Party", November 21, 1987; 1 audiocassettes (Box 54)
    - Tom Hemingway, Narration of "Moving Archives,", 1991; 1 audiocassettes (Box 54)
    - Margot Halsted, Band Carillon, 1990; 1 audiocassettes (Box 54)
    - 2nd European Conference on Archives, 1989; 12 audiocassettes (Box 54)
      (includes Conference program)
    - Provenance and Hierarchy: Archival Principles of Organization and Description featuring Mary Jo Pugh., 1982-03-15; 2 videotapes (U-matic) (Box 54)
      - Tape 1, [87245-30]
      - Tape 2, [87245-31]
    - Michigan Media Panel Discussion, November 8, 1990; [87245-32]; 2 videotapes (VHS (TM)) (Box 54)
    - 70th Anniversary Commemoration of Michigan Greenland Expeditions, March 26, 1996; [87245-34]; 1 videotape (VHS (TM)) (Box 54)
    - Jim Craven, Fran Blouin, C-Span Book Notes, 1998; [87245-35]; 1 videotape (VHS (TM)) (Box 54)
    - Edited Video Prepared by Chinese Delegation, (VHS), Summer 1999; [87245-51] (Box 71)
    - Providing a Future for the Past, by UMI (VHS) (13 minutes) [An accompanying note indicates that it features Bentley Director Francis Blouin and relates to preservation microfilming], 1990; [87245-52] (Box 71)
    - C-SPAN -- Tour of the Bentley Library (VHS), undated; [87245-53] (Box 71)
    - WJR "Night Time Detroit" featuring Hal Youngblood and Francis X. Blouin (audiocassette), 1987 (Box 71)
    - Radio interview with Ruth Bordin re: Washtenaw County: An Illustrated History, (audiocassette), 1988 (Box 71)
  - Digital Materials
    - Alice Greenwald, Passion on All Sides: Planning a Memorial Museum at Ground Zero, March 15, 2007
      (Contains a video recording of a Whitesell Lecture from the Museum Studies 2007 Colloquium "Exhibiting Controversy.")
      [Access to this material is restricted to the reading room of the Bentley Historical Library]
    - Scientific Club-Azazels Dinner, December 2008
      (Contains a video recording of James Duderstadt presenting to the Scientific and Azazel faculty clubs regarding the University of Michigan Bicentennial. Additionally, Francis Blouin speaks related to the biographical information in the Faculty Database Heritage Project.)
    - Out of the Blue: The Michigan Difference, 2010
      - Episode 306: Peace Corps, Bentley Historical Library, and Dust Storms – Nilton Renno
      - Episode 308: Green Brewery, North Quad, and Jim Craven
    - Reception in Honor of Milo Radulovich, December 14, 2008
    - State Archives Administration of China-Bentley Historical Library 2010 Joint Seminar on Archival Methods, October 2010
    - China, 2011
      (Digital photographs taken by Laura and Rex Patterson relating to Bentley delegation's trip to China.)
  - Films, Circa 1972-1974
    - Bentley Historical Library, undated
      - Building Site, [87245-41]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 71)
      - Construction, [87245-38]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 71)
      - Rackham Offices, [87245-39]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 71)
      - Willow Run, [87245-40]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 71)
    - Michigan Historical Collections, undated
      - Banquet, Groundbreaking Parade, and Masons, Part 1, [87245-44]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 55)
      - Construction and Rackham Offices, Part 2, [87245-45]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 55)
      - Moving Out and In, Part 3, [87245-46]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 55)
      - Dedication, Part 4, [87245-47]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 55)
    - Michigan Historical Collections - Moving Preparations and New Building, 1972
      - Cornerstone, [87245-48]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 71)
      - Erecting Shelving, [87245-50]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 71)
      - Rackham and Moving In, [87245-49]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 71)
    - Michigan Historical Society - Bentley Dedication Ceremonies, May 2-3, 1974
      - Part 1, [87245-36]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 71)
      - Part 2, [87245-37]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 55)
    - Moving Out and Moving In, undated
      - Groundbreaking Int. and Ext., [87245-42]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 55)
      - UM Michigan Historical Society, [87245-43]; 1 film reels (16mm) (Box 55)
- Architectural Drawings (Bentley Historical Library), 1965-2004
  The Architectural Drawings, 1965-2004 series (3 flat file drawers) is comprised of original drawings, blueprints, and blue line prints of the Bentley Historical Library. Included in the series are plans for a proposed addition to the library, 1980, and drawings related to the 2004 addition, including shelving, landscaping, and floor and site plans.
  - Two renderings, one site plan, one floor plan on four illustration boards. Undated., Pencil, ink, and watercolor (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Renderings, site plans, elevations, floor plans, Undated; 1972; 40 sheets (Blue line prints) (Map-case 1, Folder 1)
  - Details of furnishing, landscaping, mechanical floor plans, electrical floor plans, millwork, interior and exterior sections and elevations, elevator and stair details, ceiling plans, and millwork, 1972-1977; Blue line prints (Map-case 2, Folder 2)
    (Folder 1 of 3. Total number of sheets in 3 folders: sixty-three.)
  - Details of furnishing, landscaping, mechanical floor plans, electrical floor plans, millwork, interior and exterior sections and elevations, elevator and stair details, ceiling plans, and millwork, 1972-1977; Blue line prints (Map-case 2, Folder 2)
    (Folder 2 of 3. Total number of sheets in 3 folders: sixty-three.)
  - Details of furnishing, landscaping, mechanical floor plans, electrical floor plans, millwork, interior and exterior sections and elevations, elevator and stair details, ceiling plans, and millwork, 1972-1977; Blue line prints (Map-case 2, Folder 2)
    (Folder 3 of 3. Total number of sheets in 3 folders: sixty-three.)
  - Alternative proposals. Jickling and Lyman, architects. Renderings, site plans and floor plans. Twenty-eight sheets,. Blue line prints., 1965-1969 (Map-case 2, Folder 5)
    (Folder 1 of 2)
  - Alternative proposals. Jickling and Lyman, architects. Renderings, site plans and floor plans. Twenty-eight sheets,. Blue line prints., 1965-1969 (Map-case 2, Folder 6)
    (Folder 2 of 2)
  - Library addition. Renderings, floor plans, site plans, elevations, 1980; 27 sheets (Blue line prints) (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
  - Library renovations (De La Vergne cabinet)., Rendering and blueprint (Map-case 2, Folder 7)
  - Bound set of drawings. Site plan and details; sculpture court plan and details; floor plans; roof plans; finish schedule; elevations; sections; millwork; foundation plans; roof framing plan; mechanical plans, diagram, schedule and details, 1972; 47 sheets (Blue line prints) (Map-case 2, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous early design studies, plan studies, exterior elevation studies, and interior studies, 1969-1972; 75 sheets (approximate; Pencil sketches) (Map-case 2, Folder 9)
  - Courtyard Renovations, 1998; 4 sheets (Map-case 3)
  - Library Addition; site plan, exterior elevations and floor plans, 2001; 6 renderings (on 6 illustration boards) (Map-case 3)
  - Three-level shelving drawings, 2003; 7 sheets (Map-case 3)
  - Landscaping Plan, 2003-2004 (Map-case 3)
  - (Resolutions Honoring Bentley Library) (Map-case 3)
- Archived Bentley Historical Library Website
  The Archived Website, 2010-ongoing series documents the collections, events, resources, events, and people at the Bentley Historical Library. In addition to information about the University of Michigan and individuals, organizations, and voluntary associations in the state, content includes policies, procedures, important news and announcements, and the overall mission of the library. The website series is arranged chronologically and includes content captured by the Internet Archive starting in 1996. Starting in 2010, this archived website will be captured on a regular, ongoing basis as part of the University of Michigan Web Archives, hosted at https://archive-it.org/organizations/934.
  - 1996-2010
    (These versions were preserved by the Internet Archive and are made available through its Wayback Machine. The Bentley Historical Library is not involved in the collection or maintenance of this material.)
  - 2010-[ONGOING]
Related Material
Exhibit photographs, separately cataloged:
Centennial of the admission of women to the University of Michigan exhibition photograph collection (Bimu 2)
Goin' north: Black Detroit and the great migration, 1910-1930 (91183 Bimu 2)
A gallery of presidents (92261 UBImu E 17 2; finding aid in library)
Native peoples in transition: Michigan Indians in the nineteenth century (914 Aa 2)
University President's Exhibition photograph collection (UBImu B3 2)
University of Michigan and China exhibition panels (2008102 Bimu 2)
University of Michigan Sesquicentennial Celebration Exhibition photograph collection (92144 UBImu E 17 2; finding aid in library)